A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Forrest F. Hill FA547
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Forrest F. Hill
1952-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hill, F. F. (Forrest Frank) (1900-1988)
Ford Foundation
FA547
1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter document containers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Series 2 materials tranferred from the Ford Foundation and ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:016.
Biographical Note
Forrest F. "Frosty" Hill was born in 1900. He received a bachelor's degree from the University of Saskatchewan in 1923 and was awarded a PhD in Agricultural Economics by Cornell University in 1930. Dr. Hill subsequently became a professor of Land Economics at Cornell. He taught until 1938 when he was appointed Governor of the Farm Credit Administration (FCA) by President Roosevelt. He resigned in 1940, after a dispute with Secretary of Agriculture Henry A. Wallace over the autonomy of the FCA. Returning to Cornell, Dr. Hill worked for the next 15 years as a professor, chairman of the Department of Agricultural Economics, and provost of the university.
In 1955, Dr. Hill left Cornell to become the Vice President of Overseas Development for the Ford Foundation. During his time with the Foundation, he worked in partnership with the Rockefeller Foundation to establish international research centers, such as the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) in the Philippines and the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center in Mexico. From 1963 to 1978 he was Chairman of the Board of IRRI. He also served as President of the American Agricultural Economics Association and, between 1955 and 1960, sat on the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York.
Dr. Hill retired to Ithaca, New York in 1976 and died in 1988.
Scope and Contents
Dr. Hill's files include reports, correspondence, memos, photographs, and meeting minutes that document his efforts to establish and sustain international research centers, including the International Rice Research Institute in the Philippines and the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture in Nigeria. The files detail his continuing work in agricultural development and his relationships with others in the field. In addition, they contain information about the development of Foundation overseas policies and a proposed, but eventually rejected, Foundation office in Afghanistan (1956-1963).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
1. Subject Files, 1952-1966
2. Subject Files, 1953-1973
The two series arrived separately at the RAC and were processed as two separate groupings.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. Its granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. India and Pakistan were the focus of the initial grants, with a more limited number of grants issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants was initiated for the Near East region later the same year.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs such as International Training and Research and Population, became part of a unified International Division. Following another Foundation reorganization in 1983, the International Division was eliminated and two program divisions were created – the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and Developing Countries Program (DCP).
Agriculture -- Ford Foundation; Agriculture -- International centers; Ford Foundation; Green Revolution
- Subject Files, 1952-1966; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The files document Dr. Hill's years as Vice President of Overseas Development and his specialization in agriculture-related research. They contain correspondence, memoranda, reports and notes to and from Dr. Hill and grantees, colleagues, consultants and Foundation personnel.
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical
  - Asia and the Pacific (A&P) -- Afghanistan -- Re: Possible FF Involvement, 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A&P -- Burma -- Program Report, 1953-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A&P -- Indonesia -- Info Re: Closing of Office, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A&P -- International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) -- Discussion Notes, Background, etc., 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A&P -- Japan -- Re: Economics, FF Activities, Visit Plan, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A&P -- Pakistan -- Reports, Background, 1952-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A&P -- Pakistan -- Harvard-Pakistan Planning Commission -- David Bell, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A&P -- Philippines -- Re: Manila Office and IRRI, Jul 15, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A&P -- Singapore -- Re: Separation from Malaysia, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A&P -- Staffing -- Memoranda, Budgets, 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A&P -- Vietnam -- Re: Vietnam Project, Mekong Meeting, etc., 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bechtel, Stephen D. -- Correspondence Re: Bechtel Corporation, India Trip, etc., 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brookings Institution -- Correspondence Re: OD Grant for Study of U.S. Foreign Aid, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Budget -- Balance of Payments, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Budget -- Endowment Grants, 1956-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Budget -- Overhead Charges, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Education in India -- Correspondence Re: Douglas Ensminger, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Europe and International Affairs (EIA) -- USSR and East Europe -- Memorandum Re: Communism and FF Projects, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Evaluation of Overseas Program Grants, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - FF International Activities -- Organization -- David Bell Memoranda, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - FF Population Program -- Program Planning Memoranda, Press Releases, etc., 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Foundations (Other) -- Memoranda Re: Meetings with FF, etc., 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Institute for Human Reproduction -- Discussion Paper, Interim Report, etc., 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA), Nigeria -- Memoranda, Proposals, Decrees, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC) -- Brazil, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - LAC -- Caribbean --Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - LAC -- Central America -- Proposed FF Activities, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - LAC -- General -- Organization and Personnel, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - LAC -- Other Latin America -- Uruguay, Paraguay, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Middle East and Africa (MEA) -- Africa General -- Correspondence Re: Trips, Grant Activity, etc., 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - MEA -- Congo and Other West Africa -- Memoranda Re: Togo, Abidjan, etc., 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - MEA -- Nigeria -- Memoranda Re: Kingsley, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - MEA -- North Africa (Former Tunis Office) -- Memoranda Re: Personnel, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - MEA -- South Africa -- Correspondence Re: Port Elizabeth, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - MEA -- United Arab Republic (Egypt) -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Situation, Grants, 1957-1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Overseas Development (OD) Control Unit Grant Making -- Re: Grant Status, Program Meetings, etc., 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - OD Representatives' Conference, Mexico City -- David Bell -- Reports, Agenda, Program, Sep 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - OD Representatives' Meetings -- Programs, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - OD Review Seminar -- Memoranda Re: Program, Operation Janus, Mar 2-May 20, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Planning Budgets FY 1963-1965 -- David Bell, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wyzanski, Charles E. -- Correspondence Re: Trips to Turkey and Israel, Asia Programs, 1956-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Subject Files, 1953-1973; 2
  - International Rice Research Institute Photographs, 1963-1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Photos with description:
    Photos of visit by Imelda Marcos to IRRI, Palayan ng Bayan, August 1973
    President Johnson giving his speech at IRRI on October 26th. Mrs. Marcos at President Johnson's right (RFC holding umbrella for Mrs. Johnson who is hidden from view by President Marcos) (October 26, 1966)
    From left to right: R.F. Chandler, Jr., President Marcos, President Johnson, IRR-289-3 in foreground, Peta in background (October 26, 1966)
    Jennings, Beachell, and Chandler explaining new rice by the (?) to President Marcos and President Johnson (October 26, 1966)
    President Marcos delivering his talk (October 26, 1966)
    From left to right: R. F. Chandler, Jr., President Johnson, H. M. Beachell (President Marcos' head is showing over Beachell's shoulder), P. R. Jennings, A.C. McClung
    IRRI 1/6/66 (aerial view)
    IRRI 1/6/66 (group photo)
    President Johnson about to enter bus for tour of IRRI experimental fields. The President's helicopter is in the background.
    Left to right: R. F. Chandler, President Johnson, President Marcos, and H. M. Beachell
  - International Rice Research Institute Architectural Blueprints, 1961
  - International Rice Research Institute Reports, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    The International Rice Research Institute Considers Its Role in the 1970s, IRRI staff, October 3, 1969
    Trends in Rice Production in South and Southeast Asia, Randolph Parker, September 30, 1967
    An Analysis of the Interrelationships Between Land Preparation and Weeding in Lowland Rice, R. Barker and N. Deomampo, September 21, 1967
    Costs and Returns in Rice Production, Randolph Barker, October 7, 1967
  - Seminar Papers (IRRI Staff) from Forrest F. Hill Visit, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Rice Research: A Race Against Time, Dr. Sterling Wortman, December 19, 1963
    An Analysis of Factors Affecting Rice Yields, Robert F. Chandler, Jr.
    Output and Productivity Growth in South East Asian Agriculture: An Outline of the Agricultural Economics Research and Training Program at The International Rice Research Institute, Vernon W. Ruttan, December 6, 1963
  - Advisory Committee on the Application of Science and Technology (ACAST) Seminar with North American Scientists on Links with Developing Countries, United Nations (Carroll Wilson), 1968 April 5-6 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research, Technical Advisory Committee (CG/TAC), Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - International Crop Research Institute for the Semiarid Tropics (ICRISAT) Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pakistan – Agricultural Development Reports, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - President's Science Advisory Committee (PSAC) Panel on World Food Supply - Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, and Reports (2 folders), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Science Organization Development Board (SODB) (2 folders), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - International Centers and Institutes - Notes, Correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Memoranda to/from Lowell S. Hardin, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Program Action Information (2 folders), 1954-1967 (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Arthur Newmayer and Associates - Correspondence, Reports to Ford Foundation, 1955-1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Cross Reference Sheet - List of Reports Removed from Forrest Hill's Office Files, 1991 January (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Arthur Newmayer and Associates Correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Arthur Newmayer and Associates Correspondence, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 20)